Let's get straight to it.
Get it, get it 바로 본론으로 들어가죠
So the place where you can see everything that's going on and get knee deep in your data is a beautiful
모든 걸 볼 수 있고 데이터에 무릎까지 들어갈 수 있는 플랫폼은 바로 Webex and Bias라는
platform called Weights and Biases.
아름다운 플랫폼이에요
It's completely free for personal use anyway, and it's a superb.
개인적 용도로만 사용하고 아주 좋아요
You can, uh, go here.
여기로 가시면 돼요
Uh wandb is weights and biases.
원반은 무게와 편향이에요
I to sign up, create your free account.
등록하고 무료 계정을 만들라고요
You don't need to if you don't wish to.
내키지 않으면 안 해도 돼요
This is an this is completely optional.
이건 완전히 선택 사항이에요
It will allow you to visualize your training while it runs.
이게 작동하는 동안 훈련하는 모습을 시각화할 수 있죠
I strongly recommend it because it's super satisfying.
강력히 추천해요 정말 만족스럽거든요
Uh, there's no point in doing training in my mind if you can't see lots of wiggly lines.
꿈틀거리는 선이 많이 보여야 머릿속에서 훈련할 수 있죠
And believe me, we're going to have a lot of wiggly lines.
꿈틀거리는 선이 아주 많을 거예요
Uh, not not just today, but in the coming two weeks to go, it will be, uh, lots of charts, uh,
오늘뿐만 아니라 앞으로 2주 동안 차트가 많을 겁니다 무료 계정을 등록했는지 평가할
when you go to weights and biases and you've signed up for your free account or you may already have
때 유용할 수도 있고 이미 등록한 계정도 있을 수 있죠 아바타
one, uh, if you go to the avatar menu, like the settings menu and go to settings, You can create
메뉴나 설정 메뉴에서 설정으로 가면 오픈AI나 기타에서 사용한
an API key very similar to the sorts of API keys we've used for OpenAI and so on.
API 키와 유사한 API 키를 생성할 수 있어요
You can then go to the OpenAI dashboard, and I've put a link right here in the notebook.
OpenAI 대시보드로 가면 링크를 노트북에 넣어 놨어요
And when you go to that page, but in the middle of the page, there is a section that says integrations,
해당 페이지를 보시면 중앙에 통합이라는 항목이 있어요 체중과 바이어스를
and it has a section where you can put in your weights and biases key.
입력할 수 있는 항목이 있죠
And if you do that, then it's your OpenAI account is hooked up to weights and biases, and you'll be
그렇게 하면 오픈AI 계정에 무게와 편향 정보가 저장됩니다 무게와
able to watch this fine tuning process happening in weights and biases.
편향에 따른 미세한 튜닝 과정을 볼 수 있죠
And that's just great.
정말 멋져요
So I strongly recommend it but not required.
강력히 권하지만 필수는 아니에요
Assuming you did do that, then you're going to want to execute this line here which is setting up your
그렇게 했다고 가정하고 이 라인을 실행합니다 무게 설정과
weights and biases integration.
편향 통합이죠
And you can give it a name.
이름을 지어줄 수도 있고요
I'm calling the name of this project generally.
이 프로젝트의 이름을 말하고 있어요
Overall we'll be doing a lot of this project.
전반적으로 이 프로젝트의 많은 부분을 할 거예요
I call it Pricer, but for this one I'm calling it GPT pricer because it is.
저는 프라이서라고 부르지만 이 차는 GPT 프라이서라고 부르죠
GPT is fine tuned version to price products, That's why I call it Pricer.
GPT는 가격 제품의 정교한 버전입니다 그래서 프라이서라고 부르죠
So we run that.
그걸 실행하죠
Just setting up a settings right now.
지금 설정하고 있어요
But this this is it.
하지만 이게 다예요
This folks.
여러분
This is the time when we actually do our fine tuning.
이제 세세한 조율을 할 거예요
We call a new OpenAI API, which is a the big the big one OpenAI fine tuning dot jobs dot create.
새로운 OpenAI API라고 하는데 아주 큰 거죠 OpenAI의 .잡스.Create죠
And what we pass in.
우리가 지나치는 것도요
So so you remember earlier this this is what came back from uploading our file.
아까 기억하시겠지만 이건 우리 파일을 업로드하면 나오는 거죠
It has an ID.
ID가 있어요
Let me show you that it has an ID which identifies the file.
파일을 식별하는 ID를 갖고 있어요
That's the name of the file.
그게 파일 이름이에요
As far as OpenAI is concerned, we had a rather simpler name for it.
오픈아이는 좀 더 단순한 이름으로 불렸어요
This is the whole this is a file object.
이건 전부 파일 객체예요
You probably remember seeing this a moment ago.
조금 전에 이걸 보셨을 거예요
That's the file ID and that's all the details about it.
파일 ID와 관련된 모든 세부 사항이죠
Um, and that's its ID.
그게 ID예요
So we provide the ID of the training file.
훈련 파일의 ID를 제공하죠
We also provide the ID of the validation file.
검증 파일의 ID도 제공하죠
Again not strictly necessary in our case now, but a good practice and you will want to do this for
지금 꼭 필요한 건 아니지만 연습하면 좋을 거예요 나중에 세밀하게 조정할
your fine tuning runs in the future.
때 써먹으세요
Probably.
아마도요
We provide the model.
모델을 제공하죠
Now I'm suggesting GPT for many, partly because it's going to be cheaper to run it in inference.
저는 많은 사람에게 GPT를 제안하고 있습니다 추론상 실행하는 것이 더 저렴하기 때문이기도 하죠
It's just going to be a couple of cents at the most.
몇 센트밖에 안 될 거예요
Um, and partly because if you remember earlier when we ran the original models, GPT for the big guy
그 이유는 앞서 원형 모델을 실행했을 때 GPT와 미니가 비슷한 성능을
and for mini gave fairly similar performance, not a ton of difference between them.
보였기 때문이기도 해요 큰 차이가 없었죠
So it seems like we might as well fine tune the smaller one.
작은 걸 세심하게 조정하는 게 좋겠어요
The seed means that it will be repeatable.
씨앗은 반복 가능하다는 뜻이에요
Um, number of epochs.
여러 시대에서요
So this is optional.
선택 사항이에요
You don't need to specify number of epochs, how many times it's going to go all the way through the
발생된 시대의 개수나 데이터에 몇 번 사용될지 명시할 필요가 없어요
data.
스스로 결정하게 해요
I want to fix it to one because we're providing a fair amount of data, 500 data points more than than
1로 수정하고 싶어요 데이터 양이 꽤 많거든요 권장량보다 500포인트나
is usually recommended.
많죠
Um, and so I figured there's no point in doing multiple epochs.
여러 개혁을 시도할 필요가 없다고 생각했죠
If we decide we want to do more, we can just bump up the amount of training data because we've got
더 많은 걸 하고 싶다면 훈련 데이터를 늘리면 돼요 여러
lots of it, rather than doing multiple epochs.
개혁을 할 필요 없이 이미 많으니까요
This is where I specify the weights and biases integration.
무게와 편향의 통합을 지정하는 부분이죠
If you don't want to use weights and biases, just don't just remove this line altogether.
무게나 편향성을 사용하기 싫다면 이 선을 아예 없애지 마세요
Um, and then suffix is an optional thing that just will include that in the name of the model that
접미사는 선택적인 것으로 그것이 생성하는 모델의 이름에 포함되죠
Just something you can do if you want the model to have a decent name.
모델이 괜찮은 이름을 갖길 원한다면 할 수 있는 일이죠
Uh, and that's about all there is to it.
그게 다인 것 같아요
I will just mention if you haven't come across the word hyperparameters before, but I'm sure you have.
hyperperameter라는 단어를 처음 들어보신다면 말씀드릴게요 분명 들어봤을 거예요
But for anyone that hasn't, hyperparameters is what people data scientists call just the extra knobs
경험이 없는 분들을 위해 hyperperameter를 설명하자면 데이터 과학자들은 이걸 추가적인
and wheels and settings that control how your training is going to work.
손잡이와 바퀴 설정이라고 부릅니다 훈련이 어떻게 진행될지 제어하는 거죠
Any extra parameter that is something that you can set.
추가 매개 변수는 설정할 수 있어요
Try to different possibilities to see if it makes things better or worse.
상황이 좋아질지 나빠질지 여러 가능성을 살펴보죠
And that process of trying out different values and seeing if it makes it better or worse, uh, known
다양한 값을 시험해보고 더 나은지 나쁜지 보는 과정이죠 hyperpaameter
as hyperparameter Optimization.
최적화라고 해요
Hyperparameter tuning as well.
하이퍼파라미터 튜닝도요
And all of this is very fancy talk for trial and error, which is what it really is.
시행착오를 거창하게 표현한 말인데 실제로도 그래요
It's saying these are settings.
이건 설정이라고 하네요
We don't really know if it's going to make it better or worse.
더 좋아질지 나빠질지는 알 수 없어요
There's no real there's no no great theory behind this.
그럴듯한 이론 같은 건 없어요
So just try some different possibilities and see what happens.
여러 가지 가능성을 시도해 보고 어떻게 되는지 봐야죠
But no one wants to say it quite like that.
하지만 아무도 그렇게 말하고 싶어하지 않아요
So everyone says hyperparameter optimization because that sounds much more important.
하이퍼파라미터 최적화라고 다들 쓰는데 그게 더 중요하게 들리기 때문이죠
And so that's that's what we'll call it.
그래서 그렇게 부르기로 했어요
And that's why we pass in the hyper parameters.
그래서 하이퍼 매개 변수를 넘기는 거죠
And if you want to yourself do some hyperparameter optimization and try different epochs, then you
hyperpaameter 최적화를 하고 싶다면 여러 버전으로
certainly should do so.
시도해 보세요
But anyways I talk enough.
어쨌든 전 말이 많아요
We will run this guy and like that it runs and what comes back is a fine tuning job.
이걸 작동시키면 잘 작동하고 돌아와서 세밀한 조율만 하면 돼요
It says when it was created, uh, it says there's no error, which is good.
생성될 때 오류가 없다고 하네요 좋은 거죠
Not yet.
아직요
Uh, it's finished at none.
완성이 안 됐어요
Uh, here are our hyperparameters with the number of epochs.
이건 여러 개혁이 담긴 하이퍼파라미터예요
Um, that is the model.
그게 모델이에요
Um, and then everything else, the files that we passed in.
그리고 다른 것도 전부요 우리가 제출한 파일들요
Uh, now, this, uh, here will list all of the jobs that we've got right now.
여기에는 현재 우리 업무가 다 적혀 있어요
And it starts with the most recent first.
가장 최근의 일부터 시작하죠
So since we've just kicked this off, if we run this, we'll see that this, this particular job, um,
이제 막 시작했으니까 이걸 실행하면 이 특정 작업이... 확인할 수
uh, and we can check it is because we should see that this here matches this here.
있어요 여기 이 부분이 여기 이 부분과 일치해야 하거든요
So we're talking about the same job, uh, and we can see somewhere here what's going on?
같은 일을 하는 거군요 여기 어딘가에서 무슨 일인지 볼 수 있나요?
Um, well, actually, first, let's just this job ID thing so that we don't have to keep remembering
우선 직업 ID부터 얘기하죠 계속 기억할 필요 없게요
it.
변수 작업 ID로 가져가요
Just make sure that that's what we expect.
우리가 기대하는 대로만 하면 돼요
If I print that you see this job, ID matches that there and that there.
이 작업이 보인다고 하면 ID가 저기, 저기 일치해요
This is the name of our current run the job ID that we'll use to refer to it.
참조에 사용할 현재 실행 작업 ID의 이름이죠
And we can call this retrieve, uh, to get information about what's going on.
get 절개라고 부를 수 있는데 무슨 일이 일어나는지 정보를 얻기 위해서죠
And so let me see what we can learn from this.
여기서 뭘 배울 수 있을지 보죠
Uh, somewhere here we should see that it says that it's running.
여기 어딘가에 실행 중이라고 뜨는 게 보일 거예요
Uh, but anyway, the most important thing where you really see what's going on is in the next line
어쨌든 가장 중요한 것은 다음 줄에서 일어나는 일을 볼 수 있습니다.
here, which is list events passing in the job ID, and I'm limiting it to ten events.
작업 ID로 리스트 이벤트가 전달되고 있습니다. 10개의 이벤트로 제한할게요.
And if I run this now, you really see the business.
지금 운영하면 사업이 제대로 돼요
They only have been two events.
두 번밖에 안 했어요
Um, and it's listing them in in order where the most recent event comes on top.
가장 최근 사건이 가장 위인 순서로 나열돼 있어요
So there's been two events created fine tuning job and validating training file, which is what it's
두 이벤트가 생성됐어요 미세 튜닝 작업과 훈련 파일 유효성 검사죠 지금 하고 있는
doing now.
거예요
And so what's going to happen next is that over time it's going to validate the file.
다음에 일어나는 일은 시간이 지나면서 파일의 유효성을 검사하는 거죠
And then it's going to start to train.
이제 훈련을 시작할 거예요
And that's where things get interesting.
Get it, get it, get it! 이때부터 재미있어지죠
And because it's going to take a couple of minutes before it gets to that point, I will break for the
거기에 도달하기까지 몇 분 걸리기 때문에 다음 비디오로 넘어가서 쉬도록
next video.
하죠
And in the next video we'll see.
다음 비디오에서 보실 수 있어요
Training in action.
실전 훈련이죠
I will see you over there.
거기서 봐요